[{"text": "'The Catcher in the Rye' by J.D. Salinger follows Holden Caulfield, a troubled teenager who narrates his experiences over a few days after being expelled from his elite boarding school, Pencey Prep.", "entities": [["J.D. Salinger", "PERSON"], ["Holden Caulfield", "PERSON"], ["a few days", "DATE"], ["Pencey", "GPE"]]}, {"text": "Set in post-World War II New York City, the story revolves around Holden’s encounters with various characters, reflecting his disillusionment with the adult world and his search for identity and meaning.", "entities": [["post-World War II", "EVENT"], ["New York City", "GPE"], ["Holden", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "The novel begins with Holden being expelled due to poor academic performance, which sets the stage for his wandering through New York City.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"], ["New York City", "GPE"]]}, {"text": "His isolation becomes a central theme, symbolizing his struggle with mental health and alienation.", "entities": []}, {"text": "Throughout the book, Holden interacts with multiple characters, including teachers, former classmates, strangers, and his younger sister, Phoebe.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"], ["Phoebe", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Each interaction reveals his distrust of adults and his disdain for what he calls phoniness.", "entities": []}, {"text": "He idolizes Phoebe as a symbol of innocence and sincerity, which stands in contrast to his views on the rest of society.", "entities": [["Phoebe", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Holden’s fixation on preserving innocence is symbolized by his dream of being the catcher in the rye, a protector who saves children from losing their innocence.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Key symbols also include his red hunting hat, which represents Holden's uniqueness and desire for protection, and the Museum of Natural History, a place he values for its permanence in contrast to life’s constant change and unpredictability.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"], ["the Museum of Natural History", "ORG"]]}, {"text": "Holden’s narrative reveals symptoms of depression and lingering trauma from the death of his younger brother, Allie, which complicates his ability to cope with the challenges of adulthood.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"], ["Allie", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "His internal struggles suggest unresolved grief and a fear of growing up.", "entities": []}, {"text": "The climax of the story occurs when Holden, overwhelmed, plans to run away but has a meaningful encounter with Phoebe that changes his mind.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"], ["Phoebe", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Her innocence and love provide him with a sense of purpose, grounding him and encouraging him to continue facing his reality.", "entities": []}, {"text": "By the novel’s end, Holden reluctantly begins to accept life’s imperfections and complexities.", "entities": [["Holden", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "The main characters include Holden Caulfield, who is marked by cynicism, vulnerability, and compassion; Phoebe Caulfield, his younger sister who represents innocence and serves as an emotional anchor for Holden; Mr. Antolini, a former teacher who offers him guidance and represents an adult Holden partially trusts; and Allie Caulfield, Holden’s deceased younger brother, whose memory profoundly impacts him.", "entities": [["Holden Caulfield", "PERSON"], ["Phoebe Caulfield", "PERSON"], ["Holden", "PERSON"], ["Antolini", "PERSON"], ["Holden", "PERSON"], ["Allie Caulfield", "PERSON"], ["Holden", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "The novel is set primarily in New York City, with scenes at Pencey Prep and various urban locations, emphasizing Holden's sense of disorientation and social critique.", "entities": [["New York City", "GPE"], ["Pencey Prep", "ORG"], ["Holden", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Themes of alienation, innocence, identity, and the challenges of adolescence permeate the novel, creating a poignant exploration of a young person grappling with mental health and the transition to adulthood.", "entities": []}]