[{"text": "Viserys Targaryen is the last living son of the former king, Aerys II Targaryen (the 'Mad King').", "entities": [["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Aerys II Targaryen", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "As one of the last known Targaryen heirs, Viserys Targaryen is obsessed with reclaiming the Iron Throne and \n        restoring his family’s rule over Westeros.", "entities": [["one", "CARDINAL"], ["Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["the Iron Throne", "FAC"], ["Westeros", "GPE"]]}, {"text": "Ambitious and arrogant, he often treats his younger sister, Daenerys Targaryen, \n        as a pawn, seeing her only as a means to gain power.", "entities": [["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "His ruthless ambition leads him to make a marriage alliance with \n        Khal Drogo, a powerful Dothraki warlord, hoping Khal Drogo will give him the army he needs.", "entities": [["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"], ["Dothraki", "PERSON"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "However, Viserys Targaryen’s impatience and disrespect toward the Dothraki culture lead to his downfall;\n        he is ultimately killed by Khal Drogo in a brutal display of 'a crown for a king' – having molten gold poured over his head.", "entities": [["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Dothraki", "GPE"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"]]}]