[{"text": "Viserys Targaryen is the last living son of the former king, Aerys II Targaryen (the 'Mad King'), who was overthrown in King Robert Baratheon’s Rebellion.", "entities": [["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Aerys II Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["King Robert Baratheon’s Rebellion", "ORG"]]}, {"text": "As one of the last known Targaryen heirs, Viserys Targaryen is obsessed with reclaiming the Iron Throne and restoring his family’s rule over Westeros.", "entities": [["one", "CARDINAL"], ["Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["the Iron Throne", "FAC"], ["Westeros", "GPE"]]}, {"text": "Ambitious and arrogant, he often treats his younger sister, Daenerys Targaryen, as a pawn, seeing her only as a means to gain power.", "entities": [["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "His ruthless ambition leads him to make a marriage alliance with Khal Drogo, a powerful Dothraki warlord, hoping Khal Drogo will give him the army he needs.", "entities": [["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"], ["Dothraki", "PERSON"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "However, Viserys Targaryen’s impatience and disrespect toward the Dothraki culture lead to his downfall; he is ultimately killed by Khal Drogo in a brutal display of 'a crown for a king' – having molten gold poured over his head.", "entities": [["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Dothraki", "GPE"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Khal Drogo is a prominent warlord and leader of the Dothraki people, known for his fearsome reputation and formidable combat skills.", "entities": [["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"], ["Dothraki", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "He enters into a marriage with Princess Daenerys Targaryen as part of an alliance orchestrated by her brother, Prince Viserys Targaryen.", "entities": [["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Viserys Targaryen", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Though initially aloof and intimidating to Daenerys Targaryen, Khal Drogo grows to care deeply for her, and their relationship evolves into one of mutual respect and love.", "entities": [["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"], ["one", "CARDINAL"]]}, {"text": "Khal Drogo becomes devoted to Daenerys Targaryen and her dreams, including her goal of reclaiming the Iron Throne for House Targaryen.", "entities": [["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"], ["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["the Iron Throne", "FAC"], ["House", "ORG"]]}, {"text": "However, Khal Drogo’s fate takes a tragic turn after he sustains a serious wound in a skirmish, which becomes infected.", "entities": [["Khal Drogo’s", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "A healer named Mirri Maz Duur performs a ritual that leaves Khal Drogo in a vegetative state, robbing him of his strength and dignity.", "entities": [["Mirri Maz Duur", "PERSON"], ["Khal Drogo", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Heartbroken, Daenerys Targaryen ends Khal Drogo’s life mercifully, signaling both the end of her first love and a significant turning point in her journey.", "entities": [["Daenerys Targaryen", "PERSON"], ["Khal Drogo’s", "PERSON"], ["first", "ORDINAL"]]}, {"text": "King Joffrey Baratheon is the eldest son of Queen Cersei Lannister and, officially, King Robert Baratheon, though he is actually the result of an incestuous relationship between Queen Cersei and her twin brother, Ser Jaime Lannister.", "entities": [["King Joffrey Baratheon", "PERSON"], ["Queen Cersei Lannister", "PERSON"], ["King Robert Baratheon", "PERSON"], ["Queen Cersei", "PERSON"], ["Ser Jaime Lannister", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "Joffrey Baratheon's personality is marked by sadism, cruelty, and impulsive behavior, traits that make him a despised ruler and widely loathed by the people of Westeros.", "entities": [["Joffrey Baratheon's", "PERSON"], ["Westeros", "GPE"]]}, {"text": "Following King Robert Baratheon’s death, Joffrey Baratheon takes the throne and quickly reveals himself as a tyrannical ruler, prone to rash decisions and heedless of the advice given by those around him.", "entities": [["Robert Baratheon", "PERSON"], ["Joffrey Baratheon", "PERSON"]]}, {"text": "His cruelty is particularly directed at Lady Sansa Stark, his former fiancée, whom he torments and humiliates on multiple occasions.", "entities": [["Lady Sansa Stark", "ORG"]]}, {"text": "As king, he alienates his allies and fosters unrest with his reckless brutality.", "entities": []}, {"text": "Joffrey Baratheon’s reign ends abruptly when he is poisoned at his wedding feast to Margaery Tyrell, an event known as the 'Purple Wedding' which brings relief to many who suffered under his rule.", "entities": [["Joffrey Baratheon’s", "PERSON"], ["Margaery Tyrell", "PERSON"], ["Purple Wedding'", "WORK_OF_ART"]]}, {"text": "His death marks a turning point in the power struggles of King’s Landing.", "entities": [["King’s Landing", "ORG"]]}]